Joseph Charles Muhler papers, 1919-1997 C356
Indiana University Archives
Joseph Charles Muhler papers
1919-1997
1955-1977
Indiana University Archives
Muhler, Joseph Charles, 1923-
C356
25.6 cubic feet 27 boxes
Joseph C. Muhler was an assistant professor of chemistry at Indiana University from 1951 to 1972, and research professor of dental science and director of the School of Dentistry's Dental Research Institute from 1972 until his retirement in 1984. Muhler was the leader of the team that developed the original formula for Crest toothpaste in the 1950s, and his interests included that of preventative dentistry and its practices. The collection consists primarily of papers related to Dr. Muhler's research interests and his activities at IU, including original research, publications, correspondence, teaching files, student theses and materials relating to professional organizations. Records related to his Crest research are included in the collection.
Access Restrictions
Select files are closed to researchers; these are indicated in the finding aid.
Advance notice required for access.
Biographical Note
Born December 22, 1923 in Fort Wayne, Indiana, Joseph Charles Muhler attended Indiana University from 1942 until 1944 when he was drafted into the Navy. After World War II, he returned to Indiana University through support of the Navy as a dental student. In 1948, he received his D.D.S. followed by a Ph.D. in chemistry in 1951. He joined the IU chemistry faculty in 1951 as an assistant professor and in 1978 was named research professor of dental science and director of the School of Dentistry's Dental Research Institute, where he remained until retirement in 1984. A proponent of the practice of preventative dentistry, Dr. Muhler assisted in the development of the first preventative dentistry program at Indiana University.
Dr. Muhler, teamed with IU professors Harry Day and William Nebergall, developed the original formula for Crest toothpaste in the 1950s. Dr. Muhler began the development of the product in 1945 and continued his research throughout graduate school. Dentists of that period believed that fluorides, specifically sodium fluoride, were the solution to tooth decay. Dr. Muhler researched over 150 fluoride compounds and eventually proved stannous fluoride was the most effective compound in hardening tooth enamel and protecting it. Impressed with Dr. Muhler's research, Procter and Gamble underwrote the research in 1949.
Through clinical field tests on Bloomington, Indiana school children, the effectiveness of stannous fluoride was proven, and the Indiana University Foundation received a patent for the product. Licensed to Procter and Gamble, the product was branded as Crest and was distributed nationally in 1956. In 1960 the American Dental Association's Council on Dental Therapeutics endorsed Crest as an effective preventative measure against tooth decay. Dr. Muhler, Dr. Day, and Dr. Nebergall received royalties from the sales of Crest and designated that a percentage of the royalties would be received by the IU Foundation.
Beyond the accomplishment of the development of Crest, Dr. Muhler's had extensive book chapters, books, and textbooks on dentistry related subjects. Significant books include Fifty-Two Pearls and Their Environment and A Textbook of Biochemistry for Dental Students. Beyond his association with Indiana University, Dr. Muhler held numerous consultant positions with major companies such as Coca-Cola and S.C. Johnson and Sons, as well as with the various branches of the United States military. Muhler claimed to hold over 800 patents nationally and internationally. Dr. Muhler died on December 24, 1996.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into five series: Research, Publications, Subject files, Correspondence, and Audio-visual.
Scope and Content Note
The papers for Joseph C. Muhler are organized into five series; Research, Publications, Subject, Correspondence, and Audio-visual.
The first series, Research, is arranged alphabetically and consists of a wide variety of records related to Muhler's research projects. This is the largest series in the collection. Included in this series is original research such as dental charts, x-rays, and data charts; reports regarding the findings for specific projects; correspondence between Muhler and specific companies or Indiana University in relation to his studies; and permission forms and cost projections. Materials are organized by specific project when possible or by company when there are a variety of projects for the same company. Included in the wide variety of projects are those for chewing gum, mechanical toothbrushes, and fortified consumption products. Prominently featured in this series is Muhler's research materials related to the development of Crest. Many of the folders containing data, such as charts and statistical representations, have very general folder titles as Muhler did not relate these materials to specific projects.
The second series, Publications, is arranged alphabetically and contains a large variety of journal publications, articles and manuscripts written by Muhler. Included in this series are draft and completed copies of several of Muhler's books, such as Fifty-Two Pearls and Their Environment and Textbook of Biochemistry for Dental Students and a wide variety of articles related to Muhler's studies with stannous fluoride and preventative dentistry practices.
Arranged alphabetically, the third series, Subject files, consists of a wide variety of materials related to Muhler's work at Indiana University, such as his teaching files; his records on the development of a program in preventative dentistry, student theses; his records related to the Institute for Advanced Study; his records on participation in various organizations, and records relating to Muhler's philanthropic endeavors, including his work with the Sisters of the Woods, the IU Alumni Family Camp, and his donations to the Indiana University Foundation.
The fourth series, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically and includes correspondence with a wide range of individuals and organizations. Included in this series is correspondence with Herman B Wells, Harry Day, and with representatives of the United States Navy and Army.
The final series, Audio-visual, consists of a variety of titled and untitled 16 mm film reels. Included in this series are commercials for Fresh Look products and television spots on fluoride.
Separated Material
Indiana University publications not related to Dr. Muhler's research and professional interests have been removed from the collection.
Approximately 100 photographs have been transferred to the photograph collection. Included in the photographs are what appear to be press images, images of Muhler receiving awards, and personal family photographs.
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 97/101
Provenance
Transferred from Mrs. Joseph C. Muhler to the University Archives October 1997.
Appraisal
When boxing up the records at Dr. Muhler's home, there were file cabinets full of children's x-rays, presumably for his Crest research. Only a sampling of these records were retained (Boxes 25-26).
Dentistry --Research --Indiana --Bloomington.; Dentistry --Study and teaching --Indiana --Bloomington.; Preventative dentistry --Research --Indiana --Bloomington.; Chemistry teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Indiana University, Bloomington -- Faculty -- Archives; Muhler, Joseph Charles, 1923- -- Archives; Muhler, Joseph Charles, 1923- -- Correspondence
- Research, 1940-1992; undated (Box 1)
  - A and B Classification of Subjects, undated (Box 1)
  - Acidic Beverages on Enamel and Caries, Minute Maid Orange Co. c/o Coca-Cola Co., 1968-1972; undated (Box 1)
  - Air Force, Norm Harris, 1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Air Force #2, Drs. Bixler and Spear, Initial 6 Months and 1 Year Charts (Box 1)
    - 1-275, 1961; (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - 276, 1961-1962; (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 551-825, 1961; (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 826-1000, 1961-1962; (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1000-1275, 1961-1962; (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1276-1550, 1961-1962; (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1551-1600, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Air Force #2, Drs. Bixler and Spear, Initial 6 Months and 1 Year Charts (Box 2)
    - Drops- No 6 mo. Exam or Prophy, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Initial Drops, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Alfalfa, Fertilizer, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
  - Aluminum and Dental Caries, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Aluminum Containing Chewing Gum, McDennan, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Aluminum Dental Rinse (Box 2)
    - Clinical, McDennan/Crotty (Akron, Burket and Mentone), 1982-1984 (Box 2)
    - Clinical Correspondence with Personnel, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence in Reference to Aluminum Dental Rinse- Gum Disease, 1982-1983; undated (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, McDennan/Crotty, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
  - Amurol Clinical (Box 2)
    - No. 3, Calcined Kaolin Chewing Gum Compared to Toothbrushing with Dentifrice, 1980; undated (Box 2)
    - No. 4, Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of a Calcined Kaolin Containing Sugarless Chewing Gum Compared to a Non-calcined Kaolin Containing Sugarless Chewing Gum, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - No. 5 (Adults), Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of a Calcined Kaolin Containing Sugarless Chewing Gum Compared to a Control Sugarless Chewing Gum, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - No. 6, Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of a Calcined Kaolin Containing Sugarless Gum Used in Conjunction with Toothbrushing, 1982; undated (Box 2)
    - No. 7, Dental Plaque Efficacy of a Non-Acidic Calcined Kaolin Containing Sugarless Chewing Gum (cancelled), 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - No. 8, Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of a Final Formulation Peppermint Flavored Calcined Kaolin Sugarless Chewing Gum (not initiated), 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - No. 9, Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of a Final Formulation Calcined Kaolin Sugarless Chewing Gum Compared to Commercial Chewing Gums, 1983 (Box 2)
    - No. 10, Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of a Final Formulation Calcined Kaolin Sugarless Chewing Gum, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Amurol Products Co., General Correspondence (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 2)
  - Anci Laboratories, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Anti-Calculus Dentifrice, Gillette Company, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Anti-Calculus Prophy Paste, 1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Anticaries Additives, Quality Bakers, 1970-1971; undated (Box 2)
  - Anticariogenic Chewing Gum, McDennan Oral Products Inc., (Mike Crotty) (Box 2)
  - Anticariogenic Dentifrice, Colgate Palmolive Company, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - Anticariogenic Prophylactic Paste on Caries Reduction in Adults, Army, undated (Box 2)
  - Antiplaque Agents, Reneis Chemical Company, 1974-1975; undated (Box 2)
  - Army, West Point Study, 1966-1969; undated (Box 2)
  - Bimonthly Report (Box 2)
    - January-February 1976 (Box 2)
    - May- June 1976 (Box 2)
    - July-August 1976 (Box 2)
  - Bishop Industries, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Blend-A-Med, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Bloom, Mrs. George, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Bloomington and Spencer, Yearly Report, 1955-1956; (Oversized See Box 24) (Box 2)
  - Bloomington Dental Study XYZ-95, 02-200, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Bloomington Dental Study XYZ-95 (Box 3)
    - 201-399, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
      General
      Restricted
    - 400-599, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - 600-799, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - 800-999, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - 1000-1099, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - 1100-1268, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Bloomington F Procedure, 1951-1953; undated (Box 4)
  - Bloomington Floss Study, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Borp Program II, undated (Box 4)
  - Gene Brewer-Research, 1975-1986; undated (Box 4)
  - Bristol-Myers Company (Box 4)
    - 1973-1976, undated (Box 4)
    - undated (Box 4)
  - Broxodent Study- H.M. Swenson, J.C. Muhler, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Brushing Sheets, undated (Box 4)
  - Brushing Students, I and II, undated (Box 4)
  - C100 Chewing Gum, Amurol Products Company, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - Calcined Kaolin Chewing Gum, Chesebrough-Ponds, Inc., 1980-1983; undated (Box 4)
  - Calcined Kaolin Sugarless Chewing Gum, Premedent Technology, Ltd (William Lightbody), 1992; undated (Box 4)
  - Candle with Colored Flame Patent, Dr. Wilbur C. Moorman, 1953-1964; 1973 (Box 4)
  - Changes for Monthly Report, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Charts Program, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Check Up Gum, Den-tab, Minnetonka, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Chemotherapy of Dental Plaque, 1969-1972; undated (Box 4)
  - Chesebrough-Ponds, Inc (Box 4)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 4)
    - 1980, (Oversized See Box 24) (Box 4)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 4)
    - 1980-1983, undated (Box 4)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 4)
  - Chewing Gum, Topps Chewing Gum, Incorporated, 1973-1975; undated (Box 4)
  - Chicago Clinic, 1953-1954; undated (Box 4)
  - Child Dental Study X-Rays, 1961-1964; undated (Box 25, Box 26)
  - Children's Dentistry, 5 Year Program, undated (Box 4)
  - Clinical Studies, Stannous Fluoride Zirconium Prophy Paste, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Coca-Cola Company, 1971-1972; undated (Box 4)
  - Code 100 Chewing Gum, 1983 (Box 4)
  - College Brushing, 1957-1958; (Oversized See Box 24) (Box 4)
  - College Freshmen, 1955-1956; undated (Box 4)
  - Consumer Union Reports, 1973-1976 (Box 4)
  - Cooper Labs, 1978-1980; undated (Box 4)
  - Crawfordsville, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Crawfordsville Daily Records, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Dahl, 1948; 1953-1956; undated (Box 4)
  - Dahl, Expenses, June 1954-January 1955 (Box 4)
  - Dental Abrasion Testing Machine, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Dental Hygiene Program, Project PASTE (Box 5)
    - 1966-1972 (Box 5)
    - 1967 (Box 5)
  - Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of a Zirconium Silicate-Containing Sugarless Chewing Gum Compared to a Control Sugarless Chewing Gum (8103-18), 1981 (Box 5)
  - Dental Plaque Cleaning Efficacy of Sugarless Chewing Gums Containing Zirconium Silicate, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
  - Dental Radiology, Navy, Captain English, 1959; undated (Box 5)
  - Dental study Appointments, 1954 (Box 27)
    RESTRICTED
  - Dental Study Record Sheets (Box 24)
    - 1952-1957 (Box 24)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 24)
    - July 1954-June 1955 (Box 24)
    - August 1954-September 1954 (Box 24)
    - July 1957-July 1958 (Box 24)
    - December 1957-January 1958 (Box 24)
    - February 1958 (Box 24)
    - 1958 (Box 24)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 24)
  - Dental Study Sheets, undated (Box 5)
  - Dental Study Summary, 1952 (Box 5)
  - Dentifrice Flavoring, Fritzsche-Dodge and Olcott, 1973-1974 (Box 5)
  - Denture Cleanser and Anticalculus Dentifrice, International Pharmaceuticals (Marion Labs Inc.), 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - Denture Cleanser Preparations, IUF-147, 1968-1973; undated; (Oversized See Box 24) (Box 5)
  - Dog Biscuit, Ralston-Purina, Inc., 1981 (Box 5)
  - Duplicate Exam Charts Made While P & G, 1955 (Box 5)
  - E & H Topical Study, 1957-1959 (Box 5)
  - Elkhart Clinical Study, 1966-1970; undated (Box 5)
  - Elkhart Study, General Foods, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Ellettsville Duplicates, 1954 (Box 5)
  - Ellettsville School Children, undated (Box 5)
  - Enamel Fluoride Uptake Analysis, L. Perrigo Company, 1973-1981 (Box 5)
  - Endocrinology, 1974 (Box 5)
  - ESR Screening of Cariogenicity of Products, General Mills Inc., 1968-1973; undated (Box 5)
  - Evaluation of Clinical Procedures in Dentistry, Army, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Evaluation of Stannous Fluoride Dentifrice, 1960-1961; undated (Box 5)
  - E.W. Huen Company, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Examination Sheets, 1954-1955; undated (Box 5)
  - Flour Research, General Mills Inc., 1972-1975 (Box 5)
  - Fluoridation Device, Litton Dental Productions, 1934; 1957-1973; undated (Box 5)
  - Fluoride and Dental Films, 1955-1957; undated (Box 5)
  - Fluoride People not in Dental Study, 1954 (Box 27)
  - Fluoride Studies, 1962-1966; undated (Box 5)
  - Fluoride Toxicity, Report of Investigations, 1952; undated; (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Fresh Look, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Freshman, undated (Box 5)
  - Freshman Dental Class, 1956 (Box 27)
  - Fort Wayne Community Schools, Grile, Lester L., 1964-1967; undated (Box 5)
  - Fort Wayne-South Bend Caries Data, undated (Box 5)
  - General Foods, 1964-1971; 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - General Foods Children Cereal Tally, 1965; undated (Box 5)
  - Graphs, undated (Box 5)
  - Grutcher-Ryber, 1953-1955 (Box 5)
  - Hazel-Bishop Inc. (Box 6)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 6)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - 1968-1973, undated (Box 6)
  - High Polish Dentifrice Formulas, S. C. Johnson and Sons, 1970-1972; (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Howe, 1957-1959; (Oversized See Box 24) (Box 6)
  - Human Calculus/Gingivitis Clinical Study, Chesebrough-Pond's Inc., 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Human Oral Irritation/Sensitization Clinical Study, 1969; undated (Box 6)
  - Impregnated Bristle Brushes, Oral B, 1971-1978; undated (Box 6)
  - Increasing Protein Content in Corn, Kellogg Company, 1951-1954; 1971-1972; undated (Box 6)
  - Indiana University Dental Study Unit, 1952-1957 (Box 6)
  - Indiana University Dental Study X-Rays, 1954-1956 (Box 6)
  - IUPUI Committee on Protection of Human Subjects (McDennan/Crotty), 1982-1983 (Box 6)
  - Indiana University Stannous Fluoride Kit, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Indianapolis Daily Records, undated (Box 6)
  - Indianapolis Clinic, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Industrial Polishing Agents, Ford Motor Company, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Influence of Carbonated Beverages on Dental Enamel, Canada Dry, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Instructions for Therapeutic Zircate, undated (Box 6)
  - Isaac Knapp Committee on Self Administered P.P. Study, 1965-1966; undated (Box 6)
  - JLNDD, DEF, and B, undated (Box 6)
  - JLNDD, DEF, and B Carbon Copy, undated (Box 6)
  - Johnson Wax Contracts, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Johnson Wax Quarterly Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Kleen Gum, Amurol Products Co., 1984; undated (Box 6)
  - Laboratory Studies for Development of Aluminum Dental Rinse and Chewing Gum, 1982-1985 (Box 6)
  - Lactobacillus Determination Experiment, Gordon Grills (Ohio University), 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - List of Students, College, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Low Caries Index, Children, undated (Box 6)
  - Mead Johnson, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Mechanical Tooth Polishing Device on Gingivitis, Plaque and Stained Pellicle, Scherer Laboratories, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Medichem Inc., 1970-1971; undated (Box 6)
  - Methods and Assignment Chart, 1958; undated (Box 6)
  - Miles Laboratory, 1968-1972; undated (Box 6)
  - Monsanto Industrial Chemicals Co., 1972 (Box 6)
  - Monthly Reports (Box 6)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 6)
    - July 1957-June 1958 (Box 6)
    - July 1958-June 1959 (Box 6)
  - Monthly Summary, July 1955-October 1956 (Box 6)
  - Moshi Tanzania, East Africa, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Mynol Chemical Company (Box 7)
    - 1970-1972, undated (Box 7)
    - 1971-1973, undated (Box 7)
  - NaH2PO4 Enriched Presweetened Cereals Studies, undated (Box 7)
  - Names from School Office, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Nature of Calculus and Methods of Preventing It, Army, 1965 (Box 7)
  - Negro-Caucasian Appointment Data, 1965; undated (Box 7)
  - Noncariogenic and Anticariogenic Products, Nabisco Inc., 1972-1975 (Box 7)
  - Nowaski, Corrine, 1956 (Box 7)
  - One Month Index, Photo Stain, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Oral Hygiene Habits of Young Children-Dahl, undated (Box 7)
  - Oranges and Dental Health, Sunkist, 1971-1974; undated (Box 7)
  - Patent Information, 1963-1981 (Box 7)
  - Patents (Box 7)
    - 1966-1977, 1984; undated (Box 7)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Patents (Kirkland-Ellis), 1977-1986; undated (Box 7)
  - Pfitzer Inc., 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Pharmaco Inc., 1970 (Box 7)
  - Phosphates, 1967; undated (Box 7)
  - Pigmentation Data, undated; (Oversized See Box 24) (Box 7)
  - Pillsbury Company, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Plak-Away, Dow Chemical Co. and McDennan and Company, Ltd., 1979-1984 (Box 7)
  - Porta Pro (Box 7)
    - 1977 (Box 7)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - Board of Directors, 1976-1980 (Box 7)
    - Clinical Results (St. Vincent and St. Joseph) and Statistical Analysis, undated (Box 7)
    - Larry Fattaleh (Box 7)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 7)
      - 1977-1986 (Box 7)
    - Report, undated (Box 7)
  - Porta Pro II, Scherer Laboratories, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Pressurized Pik and Lactone, O'Leary Clinical, 1971-1972; undated (Box 7)
  - Pro Care, U.S. Dental Labs (Howard Alexander), 1978-1991; undated (Box 7)
  - Procter and Gamble (Box 7)
    - 1971 (Box 7)
    - Monthly Reports (Box 7)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 7)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 7)
    - July 1954-June 1955 (Box 7)
  - Program I, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Program I –B&C, Extra Sheets, Bra and Lillian, undated (Box 8)
  - Program III- Figures from Second Exam, 1953; undated (Box 8)
  - Program IVa, undated (Box 8)
  - Program V-Call List, 1955; undated (Box 8)
  - Program Va, 1956; undated (Box 8)
  - Project PASTE, 1967-1974; undated (Box 8)
  - Prophy Kit (Box 8)
    - Lava Pumice, 1951-1964; undated (Box 8)
    - Technical Support, undated (Box 8)
  - Prophy Paste, 1961-1966; undated (Box 8)
  - Prophy Paste Formula, undated (Box 8)
  - Prophylactic Cups, Wade Bullard, 1967-1970 (Box 8)
  - Prophylactic Paste, 20%, Army (Col. Russell Sumnicht), 1963-1964; undated (Box 8)
  - Prophylactic Paste, Harry J. Bosworth Co., 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Prophylactic Paste, Medichem Inc., 1972 (Box 8)
  - Prophylaxis Cup, Mynol Dental Specialties, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Dr. Radike, Procter and Gamble, 1954-1955; undated (Box 8)
  - Ralston-Purina, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Rat Dental Caries and Plaque Investigation of Dental Rinses Containing Aluminum Compounds, January 1984 (Box 8)
  - Report, 6 Month Clinical Data, 1953-1954; undated (Box 8)
  - Report to US Dental Laboratories, undated (Box 8)
  - Reports, Extra Copies, 1955-1958 (Box 8)
  - Research Files (Box 8)
    - undated (Box 8)
    - Barley Experiment, undated (Box 8)
    - A Comparison Between a Fluoride and Non Fluoride Containing Tin Salt on the Dental Caries Experience in Children, 1957; undated (Box 8)
    - A Comparison Between Salivary Gland Extirpation and Duct Litigation on Dental Caries in Rats, 1957; undated (Box 8)
    - Comparison Between SnF2, NaF, and Sarcosinate on Powdered Enamel Solubility, 1955-1956; undated (Box 8)
    - Decreased Activity of Dental Caries in Desalivated Albino Rats, 1954-1956; undated (Box 8)
    - Desal; Desal (40%), Cont (40%), undated (Box 8)
    - Dical and Pyro, undated (Box 8)
    - The Effect of Desiccated Thyroid, Propylthiouracil, Testosterone and Fluorine on the Submaxillary Glands of the Rat, Shafer and Muhler, undated (Box 8)
    - The Effect of I131 on Dental Caries in the Rat, 1955-1956; undated (Box 8)
    - The Effect of Replacement Therapy on the Dental Caries Experience of Radiothyroidectomized Rats, 1956; undated (Box 8)
    - French Lick Schools Talk (1954), 1940; 1954-1956; undated (Box 8)
    - G-H Year Data, 1954-1956; undated (Box 8)
    - The Histochemistry of the Adrenal Cortex Following Removal of the Major Salivary Glands, 1954-1956; undated (Box 8)
    - HRE, undated (Box 8)
    - HRM, undated (Box 8)
    - Male and Female on MSCD Receiving Same Amount of Food, undated (Box 8)
    - Mice Experiment, undated (Box 8)
    - Sarociside 1%, undated (Box 8)
  - Research Files (Box 9)
    - Sn I, II, III, IV, V, VI, and VII, 1953; undated (Box 9)
    - Topical Application of Stannous Fluoride on Deciduous Teeth, 1956; undated (Box 9)
    - Tryptophan Caries Study, 1957; undated (Box 9)
    - Urine Analysis, undated (Box 9)
  - Research Grant- Plaque, 1986-1987; undated (Box 9)
  - Research Projects (notice of), 1975-1982 (Box 9)
  - Roentgenology BB, undated (Box 9)
  - Saliva List, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Sarcosinate Research, 1957; undated (Box 9)
  - S. C. Johnson and Son, Inc. (Box 9)
    - 1971-1976, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Armstrong, William Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box 9)
    - Contract, undated (Box 9)
    - Expenditures, Inactive, 1971-1976 (Box 9)
    - Report (Box 9)
      - July-August 1973 (Box 9)
      - September-October 1973 (Box 9)
      - November-December 1973 (Box 9)
      - January-February 1974 (Box 9)
      - March-April 1974 (Box 9)
      - May-June 1974 (Box 9)
      - July-August 1974 (Box 9)